Neil P. Speirs Collection of U.S. Railroad Retirement Board Member Files 6215
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Neil P. Speirs Collection of U.S Railroad Retirement Board Member Files
1963-1994
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Speirs, Neil P.
U.S. Railroad Retirement Board
6215
0.33 cubic feet
0.3 linear ft.
Records (documents).
This collection contains the personal papers of Neil P. Speirs, former president of the Switchmen's Union of North America [SUNA], assistant president of the United Transportation Union [UTU], and labor member of the U.S. Railroad Retirement Board.
6333925
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
E. Parker, May 02, 2017
EAD encoding:
E. Parker, May 02, 2017
Biographical / Historical
Neil P. Speirs was born in Alberta, Canada, on December 25, 1912 and moved to the United States with his parents in 1919. He became a naturalized citizen in 1942. Mr. Speirs graduated from the University of Idaho in 1934, having majored in business and education.
Mr. Speirs began his railroad career with Southern Pacific Railroad, working in the railroad's train yards. He was first elected to the local Grievance Committee of Adjustment for Switchmen's Union of North America [SUNA], Local 98 (San Fansisco, CA) in 1950. In 1952 he was elected as a full- time officer, serving as chairman of the General Grievance Committee of Adjustment, Southern Pacific Railroad [SP]. Mr. Speirs served in this capacity until 1955, when he was elected to serve as SUNA International Vice-President. In 1959 he was elected to be President of SUNA and served as President until January 1, 1969.
On January 1, 1969 SUNA, along with the Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen, the Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen, and the Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen formed the United Transportation Union [UTU]. Upon the merger Mr. Speirs became Assistant President of UTU.
In 1969 President Richard Nixon appointed Mr. Speirs as the Labor Member of the Railroad Retirement Board. In 1974 President Gerald Ford re-appointed him to that position. He retired from the Railroad Retirement Board in 1977, but served on the Arbitration Panel of the National Mediation Board on a part-time basis until 1978.
Scope and Contents
Inclusive date range: 1963-1994
Bulk dates: 1963-1977
This collection consists of the papers of Neil P. Speirs. Included is a personal biography and newspaper clippings about his activities as a union president and member of the Railroad retirement Board. Also included is correspondence regarding his elections and appointments to various positions and honors bestowed upon him; his correspondence includes communication with the staff of three presidents: Lyndon B. Johnson, Richard M. Nixon, and Gerald Ford. Also of interest in this collection are records documeting the formation and 25th anniversary of the formation of the United Transportation Union [UTU]. These records contain pamphlets which document the history of the founding unions that united to create the UTU, reproductions of photographs, and the biographies of the various union presidents.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 6215 MB: Neil P. Speirs Collection of U.S. Railroad Retirement Board Memorabilia 6215 P: Neil P. Speirs Collection of U.S. Railroad Retirement Board Member Photographs 5034: Switchmen's Union of North America Records 5034 MB: Switchmen's Union of North America Memorabilia 5034 P: Switchmen's Union of North America Photographs 5084: Switchmen's Union of North America Additional Records 5405 mf: Switchmen's Union of North America Constitutions on Microfilm 5406 mf: Switchmen's Union of North America Arbitration on Microfilm 5447: Switchmen's Union of North America Additional Unification Minutes and Convention Proceedings 5556: Switchmen's Union of North America Additional Records 5139: UTU Records 5139 AV: UTU Audio-Visual Material 5139 MB: UTU Memorabilia 5139 P: UTU Photographs
Switchmen's Union of North America; United Transportation Union; Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen; Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen; Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen; Railroads--Employees--Labor unions; U.S. Railroad Retirement Board; Speirs, Neil P.
6333925
- Biography of Neil P. Speirs (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  undated
- History of the Railway Labor Act (Box 1, Folder 2)
  undated; post 1957 Supreme Court decision re free collective bargaining
- Telegrams re High Speed Ground Transportation Research and Development Act, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Invitation from White House, with a request for a private thirty minute meeting between Neil Speirs and President Lyndon B. Johnson.
- Newspaper Clippings about Neil Speirs, 1963-1969 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Remarks by Neil P. Speirs, president of SUNA, before the convention of the BRT, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  The 33rd Convention of the Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen (BRT)
- Speirs' Nomination to the Railroad Retirement Board, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Nominated by President Richard Nixon, confirmed by the Senate on September 17, 1969.
- Statement of Neil P. Speirs to US Senate regarding his nomination to the Railroad Retirement Board, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Dedication of UTU Marker Commemorating Formation of United Transportation Union, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Hot Springs, Arkansas, June 4, 1971. Contains pamphlet with a history of the UTU and its founding unions.
- Speirs' Re-appointment to the Railroad Retirement Board, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  by President Gerald Ford
- Letter Regarding a Plaque Honoring Neil P. Speirs, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Plaque located in collection 6215 MB, Box 1, Folder 13
- Correspondence re Speirs' Resignation from the Railroad Retirement Board, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Testimonial dinner honoring Neil P. Speirs, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Pamphlet includes reproduction of photograph portrait of Neil P. Speirs
- 25th Anniversary of the United Transportation Union Pamphlet, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 13)